<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><atom:link href="http://allentiak.github.io/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><title>Just a Blog</title><link>http://allentiak.github.io/</link><description>Just a quick blog mockup</description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 18:30:26 -0300</lastBuildDate><generator>clj-rss</generator><item><guid>http://allentiak.github.io/posts-output/2021-08-13-gsoc-partial-evaluation-report/</guid><link>http://allentiak.github.io/posts-output/2021-08-13-gsoc-partial-evaluation-report/</link><title>Clojure CLI Tools in Debian - GSoC 2021 Partial Evaluation Report</title><description><![CDATA[<p><strong>NOTE</strong>: this blog post is based on <a href="https://lists.debian.org/debian-clojure/2021/07/msg00000.html">my "Clojure CLI Tools in Debian" GSoC 2021 project Partial Evaluation Report</a>.</p><!--more--><p>Hi, everybody!</p><p>For those who don't know me, my name is Leandro Doctors (allentiak on IRC), and I'm the Debian Clojure Team's GSoC 2021 intern. My mentor is Louis-Philippe Véronneau[*] (pollo on IRC). My co-mentor is Utkarsh Gupta (utkarsh2102 on IRC). My 'no-mentor' :) is Elana Hashman (ehashman on IRC).</p><p>In this message, I will summarize what I've been up to during the Coding I period (June 7th - July 16th).</p><hr /><p>TL;DR: my updated <code>data-xml-clojure</code> package was accepted[1] in experimental on Wednesday night :-)</p><hr /><p>[1] <a href="https://tracker.debian.org/news/1244465/accepted-data-xml-clojure-020alpha6-1-source-into-experimental/">https://tracker.debian.org/news/1244465/accepted-data-xml-clojure-020alpha6-1-source-into-experimental/</a></p><p>Now, let's tell the full story.</p><p>During the first days of the "Coding I" phase, I did some research on the <code>clj</code> dependencies. And after the precious feedback from Louis-Philippe, Elana, Utkarsh, and Alex Miller (the upstream developer of <code>clj</code>, among many other libraries), I came up with the following packaging strategy.</p><ol><li>update <code>org.clojure:data.xml</code> (<code>data-xml-clojure</code>) to 0.2.0-beta6.</li><li>package <code>org.clojure:tools.gitlibs</code> (<code>tools-gitlibs-clojure</code>).</li><li>consider updating <code>libjsch-agent-proxy-java</code>, <code>jgit</code>, <code>libtools-cli-clojure</code> (all of them already in Debian).</li><li>consider packaging <code>com.cognitec.aws:*</code> packages.</li></ol><p>According to my original proposal, I should have completed all four tasks during Coding I.
Looking back, the main lesson from these past weeks is a known classic: my timeline was too optimistic: I definitely underestimated the difficulty of the packaging process. Out of the four tasks, I only finished the first one.</p><p>There were many challenges I had to overcome in order to update the library from version 0.0.8 to 0.2.0-alpha6:</p><p>This what I did:</p><p>First, I patched the source code so:</p><ul><li><ul><li>we avoid needlessly packaging <code>data-codec-clojure</code> (not currently in Debian).</li></ul></li><li><ul><li>we can ignore Clojure-Script-related dependencies.</li></ul></li></ul><p>Then, I completely overhauled the packaging code (this is, what goes inside <code>debian/</code>).</p><ul><li><ul><li>added support for automatically tracking newer releases.</li></ul></li><li><ul><li>the package now builds with Leiningen, instead of plain Java.</li></ul></li><li><ul><li>it now actually supports autopkgtest (the existing test was trivial).</li></ul></li></ul><p>All this improved the quality of the package.</p><p>I also improved the Clojure Packaging Tutorial[2] to make the process easier to follow.</p><p>[2] <a href="https://wiki.debian.org/Clojure/PackagingTutorial">https://wiki.debian.org/Clojure/PackagingTutorial</a></p><p>Looking back, it is almost as if I had started packaging the library from scratch...</p><p>But, more that what I produced, I think the most important part of all this is what I learned during these weeks.</p><p>As it was the first time I ever packaged anything in Debian, I had to learn the basics, bump by bump. (And, oh my, I surely did bump quite a few times!)</p><ul><li><ul><li>Basic packaging workflow.</li></ul></li><li><ul><li>Setup <code>sbuild</code>[3] to make it work with <code>gbp</code>[4] (when I had rebuilt bidi-clojure from scratch, I had used plain <code>sbuild</code>.)</li></ul></li><li><ul><li>Learn how to patch upstream files with <code>quilt</code>[5] (actually, via the <code>dquilt</code> frontend). This was the first really difficult task to do, since it took me quite some time to grasp it. Looking back, I think I was simply scared of breaking something :)</li></ul></li><li><ul><li>Understanding <code>debian/</code> files.</li></ul></li><li><ul><li>Understanding <code>debian/tests</code> (autopkgtest) files. This was particularly difficult, since the doc wasn't clear about it. So I then improved the Clojure Packaging Tutorial[2] to make the process easier to follow.</li></ul></li></ul><p>[2] <a href="https://wiki.debian.org/Clojure/PackagingTutorial">https://wiki.debian.org/Clojure/PackagingTutorial</a></p><p>[3] <a href="https://wiki.debian.org/sbuild">https://wiki.debian.org/sbuild</a></p><p>[4] <a href="https://manpages.debian.org/unstable/git-buildpackage/gbp.1.en.html">https://manpages.debian.org/unstable/git-buildpackage/gbp.1.en.html</a></p><p>[5] <a href="https://wiki.debian.org/UsingQuilt">https://wiki.debian.org/UsingQuilt</a></p><p>Definitely, all this was worth it. After all, my updated <code>data-xml-clojure</code> package was accepted[1] in experimental on Wednesday :-)</p><p>[1] https://tracker.debian.org/news/1244465/accepted-data-xml-clojure-020alpha6-1-source-into-experimental/</p><p>Now that I've <del>learned the basics of packaging</del> bumped enough to get my package accepted, I'm hopeful I can ramp up and catch up with (at least most of) my original schedule during Coding II.</p><p><code>tools-gitlibs-clojure</code>, you're next :-)</p><p>Thank you very much Louis-Philippe, Elana, and Utkarsh (plus a special mention to Alex) for your precious support during the last few weeks!</p>
]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate></item></channel></rss>